In this story, we are going to learn about the binary tree and its different types, a binary tree
is a tree data structure in which each parent node can have, at most, two children.
Each node of a binary tree consists of three items that data item the address to the left child and
the address to the right child exactly like this.
So we have the data item one and the address of the left child, which is indicating that two and the
child, the three, which is the address of that child.
OK, so we have this data item we have left and we have tried chart types of binary tree.
There are many types of binary trees, and we are going to discuss everyone with the next videos.
And we are going to create them in C and Java, so.
First of all, we have the full binary tree, a full binary tree is a special type of binary tree in
which every parent node internal node has either two or no children.
So either the node the parent node has either two or no children.
OK, this is the full binary tree.
No children or do children.
OK.
This is the full binary tree in next video.
We are going to create the full binary tree and go and deeply inside.
The next type is called full binary, it is called perfect binary tree.
A perfect binary tree is a type of binary tree in which every internal node has exactly two child nodes
and all the leaves nodes are of the same level.
So this is the perfect binary tree.
Do child nodes and all the nodes are at the same level?
Complete binary tree, a complete binary tree is just like a full binary tree, but with two major differences
every level must be completely filled, filled and all the leaf elements must lean towards their left.
This is leaning to the left.
So you see, like at Element six, it's app.
Left, it's not the right, so it lean to the left.
While if we consider that fully binary three, we have one and the right element, which is three.
But it is leaning to the right, so we cannot make it a complete binary, the complete binary.
All the leaf elements must lean towards the left.
And also the last leaf element might not have a right sibling.
Example a complete binary tree does not have to be a full binary tree.
This is the very important topic, and we will discuss in details when we go to the complete binary
tree unless the force.
Type is called degenerated three.
Or pathological three.
A degenerated or pathological tree is a tree having a single child either left or right?
OK.
This is that degenerated generated three, this cute binary tree skewed binary tree is a pathological
or degenerated tree in which the tree is either dominated by left nodes or the right notes.
Thus, there are two types of skewed binary tree the left skewed binary tree and the right skewed binary
tree.
The last one is balanced three balanced binary tree.
It is a type of binary tree in which the difference between the height of the left and the right sub
tree for each node is either zero or one.
OK.
We are going to discuss everything later on in that and videos.
We are going to discuss all of these types and next videos, so don't worry.
We are going to discuss them and fully detailed manner.
And we are going to run examples and run and see the codes how to create, like all of these types,
full, perfect, complete, degenerated, skewed and balanced binary tree.